<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-11T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Data analytics and astronomy portfolio by Aman Kumar </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflecting on my Presentation</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Reflecting-on-my-Presentation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflecting on my Presentation"/><published>2024-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-18T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Reflecting%20on%20my%20Presentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Reflecting-on-my-Presentation/"><![CDATA[<p>The literature review I did early on was detail-heavy on the formation and evolution of Titan. I noticed while critiquing the AI-generated review that compressing such a broad topic into a short format can often lead to missing some details. For example, how various processes on Titan fit into the wider context of planetary science or habitability. The importance of Titan’s comparisons with Earth can also be confusing for those not well-versed in the subject. Previously, I have struggled to find the right balance between being too detailed and overly brief. Transitions from one line of thought to another have been challenging, making it difficult to guide the flow of thought. After completing the first draft, I noticed the same issue: the flow was lacking. In response, I opted to cut out entire sections that dealt with complex chemical processes and physical mechanisms, choosing instead to focus more on Titan’s significance in the context of planetary exploration and habitability.</p> <p>This change felt abrupt and required significant reworking and many revisions to improve clarity and flow. It seemed to enhance the flow, but it also felt lacking in details. Details that I had spent countless hours working on. Instead, it felt very generic. However, after reviewing my presentation, I recognise that this restructuring has improved the overall quality. The changes make the narrative more coherent and accessible to a broader audience. This experience underscored the importance of keeping the intended audience in mind. Moving forward, academically and in other areas of my life, I will try this approach. It will improve the clarity and impact of my communications.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The literature review I did early on was detail-heavy on the formation and evolution of Titan. I noticed while critiquing the AI-generated review that compressing such a broad topic into a short format can often lead to missing some details. For example, how various processes on Titan fit into the wider context of planetary science or habitability. The importance of Titan’s comparisons with Earth can also be confusing for those not well-versed in the subject. Previously, I have struggled to find the right balance between being too detailed and overly brief. Transitions from one line of thought to another have been challenging, making it difficult to guide the flow of thought. After completing the first draft, I noticed the same issue: the flow was lacking. In response, I opted to cut out entire sections that dealt with complex chemical processes and physical mechanisms, choosing instead to focus more on Titan’s significance in the context of planetary exploration and habitability.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">V Band Aperture Photometry of EH Lib</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/V-Band-Aperture-Photometry-of-EH-Lib/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="V Band Aperture Photometry of EH Lib"/><published>2024-08-16T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/V%20Band%20Aperture%20Photometry%20of%20EH%20Lib</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/V-Band-Aperture-Photometry-of-EH-Lib/"><![CDATA[<p>EH Lib is an intrinsically variable pulsating star. V-band images of the EH Lib star were provided to me for a report when I was doing module ‘Observational Astronomy PHY 8001’ at USQ in early 2023. This excerpt is taken from that assignment. Using the astronomical image processor <a href="https://www.astro.louisville.edu./software/astroimagej/index.html">AstroImageJ</a> differential aperture photometry was performed on this data to produce the light curve for the EH Lib, revealing a clear variation in magnitude (flux change of 0.5 in V-band) as seen in the figure below. The star’s period, P, was determined to be ~ 0.09 days. We can see the light curve below exhibits an asymmetric shape. It indicates a rapid increase in flux followed by a slower decrease in brightness.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="PHY8001"/><category term="photometry"/><category term="artifacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EH Lib is an intrinsically variable pulsating star. V-band images of the EH Lib star were provided to me for a report when I was doing module ‘Observational Astronomy PHY 8001’ at USQ in early 2023. This excerpt is taken from that assignment. Using the astronomical image processor AstroImageJ differential aperture photometry was performed on this data to produce the light curve for the EH Lib, revealing a clear variation in magnitude (flux change of 0.5 in V-band) as seen in the figure below. The star’s period, P, was determined to be ~ 0.09 days. We can see the light curve below exhibits an asymmetric shape. It indicates a rapid increase in flux followed by a slower decrease in brightness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Peer review of ChatGPT-generated paper</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Peer-review-of-ChatGPT-generated-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Peer review of ChatGPT-generated paper"/><published>2024-07-21T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-21T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Peer%20review%20of%20ChatGPT-generated%20paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Peer-review-of-ChatGPT-generated-paper/"><![CDATA[<p>ChatGPT has come a long way in a short amount of time. But can it produce a review paper that meets publication standards? Previously, I posted a literature review addressing the question: “What is the source of nitrogen on Titan?” I then asked ChatGPT to generate a similar review on the topic: “What is the source of nitrogen on Triton?” Here is the ChatGPT-generated paper and my peer review of it -</p> <p>My Question- What is the source of nitrogen in Titan’s atmosphere?</p> <p>Revised Question- What is the source of nitrogen in Triton’s atmosphere?</p> <p>ChatGPT Question- Can you create a 2000 word literature review, using the research ques&gt;on “What is the source of nitrogen in Triton’s atmosphere?” with citatons?</p> <object data="/assets/pdf/ChatGPT_litrev.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="800px"> <p>Your browser does not support embedded PDFs. Please click <a href="/assets/pdf/your-file.pdf">here</a> to view the PDF.</p> </object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="paper"/><category term="artifacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChatGPT has come a long way in a short amount of time. But can it produce a review paper that meets publication standards? Previously, I posted a literature review addressing the question: “What is the source of nitrogen on Titan?” I then asked ChatGPT to generate a similar review on the topic: “What is the source of nitrogen on Triton?” Here is the ChatGPT-generated paper and my peer review of it -]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Source of Nitrogen in Titan’s Atmosphere</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Source-of-Nitrogen-in-Titan-s-Atmosphere/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Source of Nitrogen in Titan’s Atmosphere"/><published>2024-07-14T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Source%20of%20Nitrogen%20in%20Titan%E2%80%99s%20Atmosphere</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Source-of-Nitrogen-in-Titan-s-Atmosphere/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wondered where Titan, Saturn’s largest moon, gets its thick nitrogen-rich atmosphere? I recently finished a literature review on this very topic.–</p> <object data="/assets/pdf/Akumar_litrev.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="800px"> <p>Your browser does not support embedded PDFs. Please click <a href="/assets/pdf/your-file.pdf">here</a> to view the PDF.</p> </object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="paper"/><category term="artifacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Have you ever wondered where Titan, Saturn’s largest moon, gets its thick nitrogen-rich atmosphere? I recently finished a literature review on this very topic.– Your browser does not support embedded PDFs. Please click here to view the PDF.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presentation from literature review</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation-from-literature-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presentation from literature review"/><published>2024-07-14T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation%20from%20literature%20review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation-from-literature-review/"><![CDATA[<p>In a recent literature review, I explored the question ‘What is the source of nitrogen in Titan’s atmosphere?‘ I’ve now condensed that review into a brief presentation. Check it out!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="artifacts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a recent literature review, I explored the question ‘What is the source of nitrogen in Titan’s atmosphere?‘ I’ve now condensed that review into a brief presentation. Check it out!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Searching and Referencing workshop</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Searching-and-Referencing-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Searching and Referencing workshop"/><published>2024-06-16T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Searching%20and%20Referencing%20workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Searching-and-Referencing-workshop/"><![CDATA[<p>This workshop teaches the fundamentals of research skills- mainly searching, organizing, and referencing. After the topic selection comes a search strategy to gather all background information. We need to have a search strategy to organize our ideas, using specific keywords and Boolean operators. This helps with refining it further into a more focused knowledge pool. Evaluation of sources and referencing are also covered. Peer-reviewed and up-to-date sources are essential. Where to search is equally important. Search for academic journals through the library, Google Scholar, arXiv etc. Once I started to develop the research question, I was overwhelmed with all the literature available on my intended topic. Some were related to entirely different disciplines and expertise. However, as I kept at it, keeping this workshop in mind along with the question development workshop, it helped not only to focus my research area but also to organize my research articles to a much more manageable number. A main paper can become the base of the entire topic and using the cited references within that article we can get much more thorough picture. This was obvious, but I still need to work more on it. It has certainly thrown new light on my understanding of some topics. It also helps to get a feeling for either knowledge gaps or consensus on some things. In the past, I have always concluded that maybe this was all but moving forward I will keep this in mind.</p> <p>Once we have the necessary articles, we need a reference manager to manage and cite them in the required format. EndNote provided by the USQ can help with that. We learned how to use EndNote. I have used Mendeley Reference Manager in the past, so in some ways it was similar, though I had to always turn normal Harvard style into Harvard AGPS6 manually with that. EndNote with the Harvard AGPS6 plugin, that happens automatically, making the process less tedious and more streamlined. However, I still need to get more familiar with it because it lacks many functions and requires much more troubleshooting compared to Mendeley. For the moment, I am going to keep a similar library in Mendeley as well till I can fully get rid of further issues. If I had to start again, this searching strategy will help things move much more actively.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="workshop"/><category term="reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This workshop teaches the fundamentals of research skills- mainly searching, organizing, and referencing. After the topic selection comes a search strategy to gather all background information. We need to have a search strategy to organize our ideas, using specific keywords and Boolean operators. This helps with refining it further into a more focused knowledge pool. Evaluation of sources and referencing are also covered. Peer-reviewed and up-to-date sources are essential. Where to search is equally important. Search for academic journals through the library, Google Scholar, arXiv etc. Once I started to develop the research question, I was overwhelmed with all the literature available on my intended topic. Some were related to entirely different disciplines and expertise. However, as I kept at it, keeping this workshop in mind along with the question development workshop, it helped not only to focus my research area but also to organize my research articles to a much more manageable number. A main paper can become the base of the entire topic and using the cited references within that article we can get much more thorough picture. This was obvious, but I still need to work more on it. It has certainly thrown new light on my understanding of some topics. It also helps to get a feeling for either knowledge gaps or consensus on some things. In the past, I have always concluded that maybe this was all but moving forward I will keep this in mind.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Ethics Workshop</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Scientific-Ethics-Workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Ethics Workshop"/><published>2024-06-16T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Scientific%20Ethics%20Workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Scientific-Ethics-Workshop/"><![CDATA[<p>This workshop focused mainly on animal and human ethics, which is very important. However, it is not currently an issue in astrophysics, though with space exploration it might become relevant in the future. Whether that will involve people on board or considerations regarding animals, contamination or disease transfer to different planetary ecosystems.</p> <p>For now, as per Dr. Holt’s instructions, I am going to reflect upon a specific area of my field. Research ethics can equally be applied to academic integrity. It could involve blatant plagiarism or having some good practices that make academic and scientific research communications more robust. Academic integrity It leads to more honesty, fairness, and openness and eliminates falsification and deception. We can fall short of academic standards sometimes knowingly and sometimes unknowingly. Each item whether that is an image, dataset, table or figure – everything needs to be properly cited. Having a good reference manager, such as the Mendeley reference generator or Endnote can help us with that. Keeping a record of every idea we come across that we may want to use – jotting that down somewhere is essential. This is not only for future reference but also if you need to prove how you came up with that idea or conclusion. Good academic practises will lead to creativity, application, and development while preventing misuse and deception. Principles such as honesty, trust, fairness, and respect are essential in research. Avoiding cheating and collusion is crucial. Do not present ideas as your own without proper citations. Use proper sources, respected journals, and peer-reviewed articles. Avoid dodgy websites like Wikipedia. I have struggled in the past to formulate my own words. Sometimes, no matter what I write, it seems like I am just quoting. Learning to rephrase is an important skill, and I still sometimes struggle with it. Sometimes giving it a bit of time can help form a more coherent narrative in your mind. And stepping away from it all for some time can be beneficial.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="workshop"/><category term="reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This workshop focused mainly on animal and human ethics, which is very important. However, it is not currently an issue in astrophysics, though with space exploration it might become relevant in the future. Whether that will involve people on board or considerations regarding animals, contamination or disease transfer to different planetary ecosystems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Developing the research question</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Developing-the-research-question/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Developing the research question"/><published>2024-06-14T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-14T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Developing%20the%20research%20question</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Developing-the-research-question/"><![CDATA[<p>Reading the instructions and watching the related workshop gave me a general idea of how and where to start. When I did my undergraduate degree, it was highly focused on habitability. And Europa, Callisto, and Titan have always fascinated me with their potential for life. So, I started there, with Europa as my preference. While going through the forum posts, I found that another student had posted almost the same question that I was trying to form. Then I started looking at other questions, what else have I learned through all that literature? Titan came to the forefront with nitrogen as a main constituent of its atmosphere, its methane cycle and its subsurface ocean. Some of the things I found were way out of my comprehension, so I looked through the material, trying to focus on the side things I could continue to explore. Nitrogen on Titan looked promising, and I collected a lot of journals pertaining to the subject in a reference manager to go through all that more thoroughly. When I posted my research question and started peer reviews of fellow students’ questions, I found I could give them more focused answers than to myself. I have always had problems with writing, getting lost in the vastness of the topic and ending up doing nothing. But I was able to tell others exactly the way they should go about it. This experience, along with the helpful feedback from my peers, gave me enough insight into what to focus on and how broad the subject should be in the given timeframe. This helped me to get more specific with my question. This will surely make me well-prepared to tackle the literature review.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="workshop"/><category term="reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reading the instructions and watching the related workshop gave me a general idea of how and where to start. When I did my undergraduate degree, it was highly focused on habitability. And Europa, Callisto, and Titan have always fascinated me with their potential for life. So, I started there, with Europa as my preference. While going through the forum posts, I found that another student had posted almost the same question that I was trying to form. Then I started looking at other questions, what else have I learned through all that literature? Titan came to the forefront with nitrogen as a main constituent of its atmosphere, its methane cycle and its subsurface ocean. Some of the things I found were way out of my comprehension, so I looked through the material, trying to focus on the side things I could continue to explore. Nitrogen on Titan looked promising, and I collected a lot of journals pertaining to the subject in a reference manager to go through all that more thoroughly. When I posted my research question and started peer reviews of fellow students’ questions, I found I could give them more focused answers than to myself. I have always had problems with writing, getting lost in the vastness of the topic and ending up doing nothing. But I was able to tell others exactly the way they should go about it. This experience, along with the helpful feedback from my peers, gave me enough insight into what to focus on and how broad the subject should be in the given timeframe. This helped me to get more specific with my question. This will surely make me well-prepared to tackle the literature review.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Planning Workshop</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Planning-Workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning Workshop"/><published>2024-06-10T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Planning%20Workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/Planning-Workshop/"><![CDATA[<p>This workshop made me realise how unconventional and unorganized I am at certain things. I should have learned these skills in school. Although I do use some of these techniques intuitively, having a structured framework is very useful. This workshop suggested that I should view my studies, courses, or any big tasks as projects. Dividing the whole project into smaller tasks helps us stay on track. Setting small tasks as weekly goals can make a seemingly big project much more manageable. There are tools available to help us with that, such as calendars, to-do lists, and Gantt charts. Using these tools ensures that all tasks are completed on time and to a certain standard of satisfaction. You can see what is done, what needs to be done, and in what priority. Whether we use the agile technique, project-based technique, scientific method, design thinking, or a mixture of any or all these techniques, we must figure out what works best for us and is appropriate for the required outcome.</p> <p>Whenever I’ve done any course planning in the past, it has always been my weak point. I have always run out of time, squeezing tasks in here and there, and missing out on vital milestones. I find the Gantt chart approach very interesting for visualizing tasks and planning. Even in this course, I came to the planning part much later. I did some preliminary planning, but it wasn’t very thorough, and I still need to keep at it and adjust it to my preference and schedule. I can see where I have made certain mistakes. I tend to get bogged down doing some tasks and completely run out of time for others. Now, I have broken the project into more manageable chunks according to my current understanding of the course and my pace. However, I am still running a week late, so I will allocate more time to some tasks and try to come up to date soon. I need to work more on planning. Moving forward, I’ll try to incorporate more of this into my upcoming courses, as well as my personal and professional life.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astronomy"/><category term="SCI6103"/><category term="workshop"/><category term="reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This workshop made me realise how unconventional and unorganized I am at certain things. I should have learned these skills in school. Although I do use some of these techniques intuitively, having a structured framework is very useful. This workshop suggested that I should view my studies, courses, or any big tasks as projects. Dividing the whole project into smaller tasks helps us stay on track. Setting small tasks as weekly goals can make a seemingly big project much more manageable. There are tools available to help us with that, such as calendars, to-do lists, and Gantt charts. Using these tools ensures that all tasks are completed on time and to a certain standard of satisfaction. You can see what is done, what needs to be done, and in what priority. Whether we use the agile technique, project-based technique, scientific method, design thinking, or a mixture of any or all these techniques, we must figure out what works best for us and is appropriate for the required outcome.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amandadwal.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry></feed>